Nothing on earth could come between them.
Titanic is a drama, romance film directed by James Cameron.
101-year-old Rose DeWitt Bukater tells the story of her
life aboard the Titanic, 84 years later.
A young Rose boards the ship with her mother and fiancé.
Meanwhile, Jack Dawson and Fabrizio De Rossi win
third-class tickets aboard the ship.
Rose tells the whole story from Titanic's departure through to its
death—on its first and last voyage—on April 15, 1912.
Jack Dawson, played by Leonardo DiCaprio.
Rose DeWitt Bukater, played by Kate Winslet.
Cal Hockley, played by Billy Zane.
Molly Brown, played by Kathy Bates.
Ruth DeWitt Bukater, played by Frances Fisher.
Old Rose, played by Gloria Stuart.
Titanic is a 1997 American epic historical romance film
written and directed by James Cameron.
Incorporating both historical and fictional aspects, it is based
on accounts of the sinking of RMS Titanic in 1912.
Leonardo DiCaprio and Kate Winslet star as members of different social classes
who fall in love during the ship's ill-fated maiden voyage.
The ensemble cast includes Billy Zane, Kathy Bates, Frances Fisher, Bernard
Hill, Jonathan Hyde, Danny Nucci, David Warner and Bill Paxton.
Cameron's inspiration came from his fascination with shipwrecks.
He felt a love story interspersed with human loss would be
essential to convey the emotional impact of the disaster.
Production began on September 1, 1995, when Cameron
shot footage of the Titanic wreck.
The modern scenes on the research vessel were shot on board the Akademik Mstislav
Keldysh, which Cameron had used as a base when filming the wreck.
Scale models, computer-generated imagery (CGI), and a reconstruction of the
Titanic built at Baja Studios were used to recreate the sinking.
Titanic was initially in development at 20th Century Fox, but delays and a mounting
budget resulted in Fox partnering with Paramount Pictures for financial help.
It was the most expensive film ever made at the time,
with a production budget of $200 million.
Filming took place from July 1996 to March 1997.
Titanic premiered at the Tokyo International Film Festival on November 1,
1997, and was released in the United States on December 19.
It was distributed by Paramount Pictures in the United States and
Canada and by 20th Century Fox in other territories.
It was praised for its visual effects, performances (particularly those of DiCaprio, Winslet, and Gloria
Stuart), production values, direction, score, cinematography, story, and emotional depth.
Among other awards, the film received fourteen nominations at the 70th Academy
Awards and won eleven, including Best Picture and Best Director.
In doing so, it tied both All About Eve (1950) for the record for the most Academy Award nominations, and Ben-Hur (1959) for the most Academy Awards won by a film, making Titanic the most successful individual film in
Academy Award history (these records would be matched by 2016's La La Land and 2003's The Lord of the Rings: The Return of the King respectively, with the nomination record surpassed by Sinners in 2026).
With an initial worldwide gross of over $1.84 billion, becoming the highest-grossing film of 1997, Titanic was the first film to reach the billion-dollar mark (1993's Jurassic Park would
later become the earliest film to achieve the feat via re-releases), and was the highest-grossing film of all time until Cameron's next film, Avatar (2009), surpassed it in 2010.
Income from the initial theatrical release, retail video, and
soundtrack sales and US broadcast rights exceeded $3.2 billion.
Releases pushed the worldwide theatrical total to $2.264 billion, making Titanic the second film to gross more
than $2 billion worldwide after Avatar; as of 2023, it is the fourth-highest grossing film.
In 2017, the Library of Congress selected it for preservation in the United States National
Film Registry as "culturally, historically, or aesthetically significant".
The film explores themes of ship, soulmates, panic, shipwreck, atlantic ocean.
The tone is emotional.